Guide to the David Pierpont Gardner audio-visual collection 1973-1983
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
David Pierpont Gardner audio-visual collection
1973-1983
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0024
Gardner, David Pierpont,1933-
5 U-matic videocassettes, 1 VHS videocassette, 2 audiocassettes, 2 reel-to-reel audiotapes
The David Pierpont Gardner audio-visual collection (1973-1983) consists of instructional videos hosted by Gardner detailing research and academic life at the University of Utah. The collection also contains audio recordings, including tapes of Gardner's inauguration as University of Utah president, a position he held from 1973-1982.
David Pierpont Gardner (b. 1933) received his Bachelor of Science from Brigham Young University (BYU) in 1955, his M.A. from the University of California at Berkeley in 1959, and his Ph.D. from the University of Utah in 1966. He is a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, member of the National Academy of Education, and a member of the American Philosophical Society. Following his tenure as President at the University of Utah from 1973-1982, he became President of the University of California from 1983-1992. From 1993 to 1999, he was the president of the William and Flora Hewlett Foundation. More recently, he served as the chairman of the Board of Trustees of the J. Paul Getty Trust from 2000 to 2004. Now in his retirement, he remains an active supporter of education.
The David Pierpont Gardner audio-visual collection (1973-1983) consists of instructional videos hosted by Gardner detailing research and academic life at the University of Utah. The collection also contains audio recordings, including tapes of Gardner's inauguration as University of Utah president.
The collection is arranged by material format and by subject.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the David Pierpont Gardner papers (Accn 2006) and the David Pierpont Gardner presidential records (Acc0387).
University of Utah; Education--United States--Sources; Colleges and Universities; Moving Images; Sound Recordings; moving images; sound recordings
- What Is a University?, undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 1)
  Originally aired on KUED.
- What Is University Teaching? (part one), undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 2)
  Locally produced television program dealing with the questions of: What are the purposes, methods and results of University teaching? Who decides what good or poor teaching is? Can students be protected from poor teaching? How? How are improvements achieved? What is the ultimate value of a teacher's work? President David P. Gardner discusses these issues with faculty and students. Originally aired on KUED.
- What Is University Teaching? (part two), undated; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 3)
  In the second program of the series, President Gardner discusses university teaching with Dr. Arvo Van Alstyne, Dr. Dale Dick and Dr. Jack Adamson of the U. of U. faculty. Areas of discussion include: What is good teaching? What responsibilities does teaching carry, and how can a teacher serve his or her students? Originally aired on KUED.
- What Is University Research?, 1975 November; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 4)
  Locally produced television program. Originally aired on KUED.
- Dr. David Gardner Speaks About Civic Dialog, 1983 May; U-matic videocassette (Cassette 5)
- Technological Transfer and Universities, 1982 February 11; VHS videocassette (Cassette 6)
  6th Herbert Spencer Lecture Series on Technology and Society delivered by University of Pennsylvania president emeritus Professor Martin Meyerson.
  Alumni Hall, Towne Building, University of Pennsylvania, 3:30PM
- G. Holton Phone-in comments on NCEE, 1983 April 8; Audiocassette (Cassette 7)
- The Declaration of Independence, 1983 April 20; Audiocassette (Cassette 8)
  Soloist: James Javore
  Performed at D.A.R. Constitution Hall, Washington D.C.
- President David Pierpont Gardner inauguration (part one), 1973 November 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 9)
- President David Pierpont Gardner inauguration (part two), 1973 November 19; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 10)